Zafeiria (Iro) Moumoulidou

College of Information & Computer Sciences
University of Massachusetts
140 Governors Drive, Amherst, MA, 01003
zmoumoulidou@cs.umass.edu
https://imoumoulidou.github.io/

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research interests lie in the broad area of ethical, equitable, and responsible systems. I focus on issues of diversity, data and algorithmic fairness, while I am particularly fascinated by the areas of Fair & Explainable AI, Machine Learning, and Recommendation Systems.

EDUCATION

University of Massachusetts

Amherst, MA

Ph.D. in Computer Science, GPA: 3.98/4.00

September 2018-Present

Advisor: Prof. Alexandra Meliou

TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY OF CRETE

Chania, Greece

Diploma (5-year degree) in Electrical & Computer Engineering, GPA: 8.52/10.00

August 2018

Thesis: "Dynamic Decision Trees in a Distributed Environment" Advisors: Prof. Minos Garofalakis, Prof. Antonios Deligiannakis

RESEARCH & ACADEMIC EXPERIENCE

University of Massachusetts

Amherst, MA

Research Assistant

Fall 2018-Present

Research on data diversification and algorithmic fairness using techniques from theoretical computer science.

Megagon Labs

Mountain View, CA

Research Scientist Intern

June 2021-August 2021

Research on understanding semantics in structured datasets.

University of Massachusetts

Amherst, MA

Teaching Assistant

Fall 2021

In Research Methods in Empirical Computer Science with Prof. David Jensen.

University of Massachusetts

Amherst, MA

Teaching Assistant

Spring 2022

In Database Design and Implementation with Prof. Yanlei Diao and Prof. Marco Serafini.

PUBLICATIONS

- [1] **Z. Moumoulidou**, A. McGregor, and A. Meliou. Diverse Data Selection under Fairness Constraints. *In 24th International Conference on Database Theory (ICDT 2021)*
- [2] R. Addanki, A. McGregor, A. Meliou, and **Z. Moumoulidou***. Improved Approximation and Scalability for Fair Max-Min Diversification. In 25th International Conference on Database Theory (ICDT 2022) 🔁 🗅
- * Authors appear in alphabetical order.

AWARDS & DISTINCTIONS

• Outstanding Academic Performance Scholarship, Gerondelis Foundation, (Grant \$5,000)

2019

• Nominated by UMass CICS to apply for the *Microsoft PhD Fellowship*, (1/3 nominations)

2020

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Programming Languages: Python, Java, Matlab/GNU Octave, SQL
- Environments & Tools: PyTorch, MapReduce (Hadoop)
- Misc: Numpy, Pandas, Scikit-learn, Jyputer Notebook, Latex

PROFESSIONAL SERVICE & OUTREACH

- External Reviewer: VLDB 2021 (demonstration track), EDBT 2022 (demonstration track), VLDB 2022, SIGMOD 2022, VLDB 2023, EDBT 2023
- Journal Reviewer: The VLDB Journal (VLDBJ 2022), International Journal of Data Science and Analytics
- Volunteer: PhD Applicant Support Program at CICS UMass, Undegraduate Research Night

INVITED TALKS

• Cornell Database Seminar	April 2023
• Megagon Labs	June 2021

GRADUATE COURSEWORK

• Business Process Optimization, with Prof. Ahmed Ghoniem (A)	Fall 2022
• Advanced Topics in Natural Language Processing, with Prof. Brendan O'Connor (audit)	Spring 2021
• Advanced Machine Learning, with Prof. Benjamin Marlin (A)	Fall 2020
• Randomized Algorithms, with Prof. Andrew McGregor (A)	Spring 2020
• Optimization in Computer Science, with Prof. Madalina Fiterau (A)	Spring 2020
• Neural Networks: A Modern Introduction, with Prof. Erik Learned-Miller (A)	Fall 2019
• Research Methods in Empirical Computer Science, with Prof. David Jensen (A)	Fall 2019
• Advanced Algorithms, with Prof. Ramesh Sitaraman (A-)	Spring 2019
• Database Design & Implementation, with Prof. Gerome Miklau (A)	Fall 2018
• Machine Learning, with Prof. Brendan O'Connor (A)	Fall 2018

Notable Undergraduate Coursework

- Special Topics in Database Systems (10/10) (graduate course)
- Human Computer Interaction (10/10)
- Convex Optimization (9/10)
- Information Theory (10/10)
- Statistical Signal Processing (9/10)
- Probability Theory & Statistics (9.5/10)

LANGUAGES

- Greek: Native
- English: Certificate of Proficiency in English C2, University of Cambridge, University of Michigan
- Spanish: Diploma Superior de Español Como Lengua Extranjera C2, Instituto Cervantes
- German: Goethe-Zertifikat B2, Goethe-Institut